A Guide to the Lee Morrison Papers, 1946-2012: SC 0215
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Lee Morrison Papers,
1946-2012
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Morrison, Lee (Lonnie Leotus Morrison), 1926-2015
SC 0215
1.32 cubic feet; 4 boxes
The material present in this collection comprise the personal papers of Dr. Lee Morrison. These files contain materials from conferences, speeches, diplomas and awards, photos, reports on women's issues in sports and education, and personal reflections.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Lee Morrison in October 2012.
Appraisal
Four boxes of trophies, plaques, awards, and realia were not retained by Special Collections.
Bio/Historical Note
Dr. Lonnie Leotus "Lee" Morrison (1926-2015) was a professor, coach, and administrator at Madison College starting in 1954 until she retired in 1989. She graduated from Georgia State College for Women in 1948 with a B.S. in Education. She then went on to get her M.A. from George Peabody College for Teachers in 1951. After acquiring the position at Madison College, she received her doctorate at Indiana University in 1964. In 1967, she became the Coordinator of Women's Sports for Madison College. From 1972 until her retirement in 1989 she served as the Associate Director of Athletics for James Madison University. Dr. Morrison dedicated her professional career to promoting equality in collegiate sports. After the passage of Title IX, an educational amendment that banned sex discrimination in any program receiving federal aid, she was still involved in many organizations that fought to end sex discrimination in school athletics. She was a member of the Virginia Association for Girls and Women in Sport and a founding board member of the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW), for which she later served as president. She worked on numerous committees at the state, regional, and national level for the National Association for Girls and Women in Sport. She also served on President Ronald Carrier's Think Tank on Women's Issues at JMU. Throughout her career she won many awards for her dedication. After retirement, she helped establish the Morrison-Bruce Center for the Promotion of Physical Activity for Girls and Women on the JMU campus.
Scope and Content
The Lee Morrison Papers, 1946-2012, comprise the personal and professional papers of Dr. Lee Morrison. These files relate to conferences, speeches, diplomas and awards, photographs, reports on women's issues in sports and education, Title IX, President Ronald Carrier's Think Tank on Women's Issues at JMU, and personal reflections. There are also transcripts of interviews conducted by Chuck Walcott, Virginia Tech professor of political science, with Lee Morrison dated 1996.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in the same order in which it was donated.
Separated Material
A copy of the brochure "Sexism in Higher Education: The James Madison Perspective" (1990) was separated from the collection and cataloged.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Morrison, Lee, 1926-2015 -- Correspondence.; Madison College -- Faculty -- Correspondence; James Madison University -- Faculty -- Correspondence; Physical education for girls; Physical education for women; College sports for women; College sports
Genre and Form Terms:
Speeches (Documents); Photographs; Letters (correspondence); Research (documents); Reports
- Portrait photographs, 1988-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Class presentations, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Diplomas, awards, and certificates, 1946-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mary Baldwin, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1990 Honorary Degree, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- ACE Conference Agenda, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Women in Sport - A progress report, Bill Gilbert and Nancy Williamson, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- NA Congress Philly, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Germany October 9-28, 1977, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Caroline Sinclair portfolio, 1969-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Honors, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- AIAW president pictures, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Commencement 8/90, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- UNESCO trip to Paris, France 5/21/78, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Comp. speeches, 1974-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Personal resume - L. Leotus Morrison, 1962-2009 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- October weekend, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- NACWAA, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reunion - Florida 2/11-14/09, 1982-2009, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- AIAW documents 1974, 1973-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Women's Fitness Center, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Poems and thoughts, 1962-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Speech material, 1972-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Essay, 1959-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Chuck Walcott - AIAW, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Morrison-Bruce Endowment, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Other centers, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Morrison-Bruce Center, 1966-2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- LLM - Odds & Ends, 2008-2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Speech - G. Hunt '08, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 2011 - Women in Sports, 2010-2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Articles, 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Title IX research, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Title IX - timelines/sport history, 2004-2007 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Greater Savannah Athletic Hall of Fame, 1990-2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Virginia Hall of Fame, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- AIAW history, 1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Personal reflections, 1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Resume, 1983-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Smith magazine, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Think Tank on Women's Issues, 1988-2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Think Tank on Women's Issues, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Think Tank Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Binder, 1999-2007, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Sweet Briar (2005), 2005, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Smith archives, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Odds and Ends, 2002-2011 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Women's Colleges and Athletics, September 2002 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Title IX under George Bush, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Speeches and articles, 1966-2011 (Box 4, Folder 15)